Guide to the Mary Jean Bowman Papers 1916-1998
University of Chicago Library
Bowman, Mary Jean. Papers
1916-1998
21 linear feet (42 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Mary Jean Bowman (1908-2002) University of Chicago economist best known for her work on the economics of education. The Mary Jean Bowman papers contain published work by Bowman as well as manuscript drafts, notes, and research and teaching materials. The collection also includes reprints and manuscripts by other scholars, correspondence, and some personal files.
Information on Use
Access
Series V includes student evaluative material restricted until 2062 and personal financial material restricted for fifty years. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Mary Jean Bowman was born in New York City in 1908 and raised in Newton Center, Massachusetts. She received a B.A. in economics from Vassar College in 1930, an M.A. in economics from Radcliffe College in 1932, and a Ph.D. in economics from Harvard University in 1938. During the 1930s Bowman did casework and research at the Massachusetts Women’s State Prison and began teaching at Iowa State College. In 1943 Bowman, along with her husband C. Arnold Anderson, Theodore Schultz. D. Gale Johnson and others left Iowa State during the “oleomargarine controversy.” (During World War II, Iowa State College faculty published a pamphlet recommending the use of oleomargarine during wartime. Under pressure from the state dairy industry, the college president urged the faculty to revise the pamphlet.) Bowman then worked as a price economist for the federal Bureau of Labor Statistics and as a visiting lecturer at the University of California, Berkeley before moving to Chicago with her husband in 1949. Because C. Arnold Anderson was a faculty member in the Education department at the University of Chicago, Bowman was not awarded a faculty appointment in the Economics department until 1958 after the University relaxed nepotism rules. She did, however, teach as an Associate Professor in the Economics department prior to 1958. In 1969 she was awarded a joint appointment in the Economics and Education departments.
Bowman was best known for applying human capital theory to the study of education. She published six books and more than seventy five articles over the course of her career. With George Leland Bach, she co-authored the textbook Economic Analysis and Public Policy, which was the most widely used college economics textbook in the 1940s and 1950s. She published influential research on income distribution in the 1950s and produced a major study of the economics of poverty-stricken Eastern Kentucky in the 1960s. She also researched internationally, and published books on the Ivory Coast and Japan as well as numerous articles on economics and education in developing countries. She collaborated with her husband (who directed the University’s Comparative Education Center) to publish work on economics and education based on both domestic and international research.
Mary Jean Bowman died in Chicago in 2002 at age 93.
Scope Note
The Mary Jean Bowman papers include reprints of scholarly articles, manuscripts, notes, correspondence, and other documents. Series I contains work by Mary Jean Bowman, including manuscripts and reprints of articles and books, ranging from 1929 to 1998. Included are works authored by Bowman alone as well as those jointly authored with other scholars, including Bowman’s husband C. Arnold Anderson. Series II contains a variety of research and teaching materials. Included are subject files containing publications and notes on various topics, as well as files of statistical data, syllabi and notes for several courses. Series III contains copies of Bowman’s vitae, information from several conferences, correspondence, miscellaneous notes, and material for a volume about C. Arnold Anderson that Bowman compiled for Anderson’s memorial service in 1990. Series IV contains work by other scholars, including reprints from scholarly journals as well as manuscript drafts. Bowman organized some of these materials by author; the remainder have been grouped into manuscripts organized alphabetically by author (or lead author) name and reprints organized alphabetically by author (or lead author) name. Series V contains restricted material. Box 43 contains financial documents and is restricted for 50 years from date of record creation. Box 44 holds recommendation letters and is restricted for 80 years from date of record creation.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
C. Arnold Anderson. Papers
Subject Headings
Bowman, Mary Jean; Anderson, C. Arnold (Charles Arnold), 1907-; Economics; Economic development; Comparative education; Japan -- Education; Côte d'Ivoire; Kentucky; Mexico -- Education
INVENTORY
- Series I: Writing by Bowman
  - "Restriction in the Rubber and Coffee Industries," 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1939-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts and reprints, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript on Kentucky, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript on Kentucky, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript on Kentucky, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts. undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts. undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts. undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript on Ivory Coast, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript on Ivory Coast, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts by Mary Jean Bowman and C. Arnold Anderson, 1949-1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Human Resource Development and Economic Development," Bowman and Anderson, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts by Mary Jean Bowman and C. Arnold Anderson, 1961- 1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Interdisciplinary Aspects of the Theory of Regional Development," Bowman and Anderson, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Interdisciplinary Aspects of the Theory of Regional Development," Bowman and Anderson, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts by Mary Jean Bowman and C. Arnold Anderson, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Commentary on Aid Educational and Manpower Programs in Africa," Bowman and Anderson, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts by Mary Jean Bowman and C. Arnold Anderson, 1966- 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Students, Teachers, and Opportunity Perceptions in Kenya," Volume I, Bowman and Anderson, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Students, Teachers, and Opportunity Perceptions in Kenya," Volume II, Bowman and Anderson, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts by Mary Jean Bowman and C. Arnold Anderson, 1969- 1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Notes on a Trip through China," Bowman and Anderson, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "The Participation of Women in Education in the Third World," Bowman and Anderson, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "The Participation of Women in Education in the Third World," Bowman and Anderson, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "The Participation of Women in Education in the Third World," Bowman and Anderson, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Memorandum on IFER," Bowman and Anderson, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Mass Higher Education: Some Perspectives from Experience in the U.S., Bowman and Anderson, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bowman and Anderson, miscellaneous manuscripts and notes (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bowman and Anderson, miscellaneous manuscripts and notes (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Economic Analysis and Public Policy, Bowman and Bach, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Communication and the Ecology of Mountain Development," Bowman and Plunkett, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Communication and the Ecology of Mountain Development," Bowman and Plunkett, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Communication and the Ecology of Mountain Development," Bowman and Plunkett, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Communication and the Ecology of Mountain Development," Bowman and Plunkett, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Communication and the Ecology of Mountain Development," Bowman and Plunkett, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts, Bowman and Plunkett, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "A Theoretical and Empirical Analysis of Vocational Preparation in Japan," Bowman et. al., 1970 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Frontiers of Economic Research and Development for the 1970s," Bowman et. al., 1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Frontiers of Economic Research and Development for the 1970s," Bowman et. al., 1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Reports to the World Bank, Bowman et. al., 1978 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Education and Income," Bowman et. al., 1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Human Resources in Africa," Bowman et. al., 1982 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts, Bowman et. al., 1983-1984, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Emergence of a Modern Labor Force in the Ivory Coast," Bowman and Clignet, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "Fertility, Child Employment and Schooling in Mexico," Bowman and Goldblatt, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "Fertility, Child Employment and Schooling in Mexico," Bowman and Goldblatt, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts on Mexico, Bowman and Goldblatt (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mexico notes and manuscripts, Bowman and Goldblatt (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - "The Political Economy of Public Support of Higher Education," Bowman et. al., 1986 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - "The Political Economy of Public Support of Higher Education," Bowman et. al., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts on Japan, Bowman et. al., undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - "Readings on Education and Economic Development," Bowman et. al., undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Series II: Research & Teaching
  - China, 1981-1991 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Altruism, 1986-1989 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Rational Expectations, 1977-1986 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Uncertainty, 1969-1985 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Income Distribution, 1964-1983 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Income Distribution and Public Policy, 1969-1983 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Education and Income, 1916-1971 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Education and Income, 1972-1981 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Education History, 1946-1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Economics of Education, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Child Development, 1996-1997 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Economic and Time, 1965-1972 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Africa, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Methodology, 1969-1986 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Non-formal Education, 1973-1976 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Poverty and Development, 1980-1988 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Growth, Inequality, and Income Distribution in Less Developed, Countries, 1960-1980 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Growth, Inequality, and Income Distribution in Less Developed, Countries, 1980-1988 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Rationality and Economics, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Education and Earnings, 1969-1987 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Earnings and Labor Markets, 1976-1980, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Migration, 1980-1987 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Economic Theory, 1978-1984 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - World Bank Africa policy papers, 1984-1986 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Japan, reprints and manuscripts (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Japan, reprints, 1962-1992 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Income Distribution and Mobility, 1973-1981 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Growth, Demographics and Income Distribution, 1978-1983 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Education and Employment, 1977-1987, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Income Distribution in Developing Countries, 1973, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Education and Inequality, 1973-1984, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Upsala VI, Notes (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Dynamic growth theory, manuscripts and notes (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Dynamic growth theory, manuscripts and notes (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Yugoslavia, notes, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Brownfields, notes and research (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - NIE report, correspondence and notes (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Option values, notes (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Rural development, notes (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous references (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Japan, notes (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Japan, notes (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous tables (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Charts on Women (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Zero order correlation matrix of 1970 data (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Data sets, 1968-1970, 1984, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Charts, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Data sets, 1984-1987 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Data sets, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Data sets, 1986-1987 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Data sets, 1985-1986 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Data sets, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Data sets, 1986-1978 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - State equations data sets, 1983-1986 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - State univariate tables (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Data sets, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - State univariates (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Data sets, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Correlations, 1960 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Data sets, 1983, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Data sets, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Data sets. 1985 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Health data (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Data sets, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Data sets, 1983-1985 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Data sets, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Data, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Course materials, Education 322 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Course materials, Education 326 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Course materials, Human Resources, Berkeley, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous course notes (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Series III: Personal Files, Correspondence, and Miscellaneous
  - Bowman vitae, publications, employment history (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Bowman, awards, 1982, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1988 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Address lists (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Letters for C. Arnold Anderson memorial service, 1990 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - "Bits of the Lives of Students and Close Associates," C. Arnold, Anderson memorial service, 1990 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago Comparative Education Center (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - National Institute of Education Conference, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Symposium on Expectations and Demands for Places in Higher Education Institutions, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous conferences (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Compton Lecture Series, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Press coverage of University of Chicago economists (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, information, and statements about T.W. Schultz (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous vitae (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Writing by Others
  - Gary Becker, reprints and manuscripts,1966-1977 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Gary Becker, reprints and manuscripts,1981-1993 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Gary Becker, vitae and reviews (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Yoram Ben-Porath, reprints and manuscripts, 1980 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Mark Blaug, reprints, 1975-1984 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Mary Brinton, manuscript, 1990 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Martin Carnoy, reprints, 1970, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Claudio de Moura Castro, manuscripts, 1989, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - D.P. Chaudri, manuscripts, 1969, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Carmel Chiswick, manuscript, 1975 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - David Cooper, reprints, 1980 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - G.M. Criel, manuscript, 1981 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Ronald Dore, reprints and manuscripts, 1962-1978 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Ronald Dore, manuscripts on Japan, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Gary S. Fields, reprints and mansucripts, 1976-1980 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Penelope Flores, vitae and manusripts, undated (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Bruce Harker, mansucrips, undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Stephen Heyneman, reprints, 1978-1980 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Stephen Heyneman, reprints and manuscripts, 1980-1984 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Stephen Heyneman, reprints and manuscripts, 1985-1995 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Torsten Husén, reprints, 1975, 1977 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - William Hyde, reprints and manuscripts, 1975-1979 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Harry G. Johnson, reprints and manuscripts, 1971, undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Dale Jorgenson, manuscripts, 1977, 1987 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Simon Kuznets, reprints and manuscripts, 1972-1977 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Henry Levin, reprints, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Assar Lindbeck, manuscripts, 1986-1987 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Robert Lucas, vitae, reprints, press coverage, 1977-1995 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Donald McCloskey, vitae, reprints, 1972, 1984, undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Jacob Mincer, reprints and manuscripts, 1958-1989 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Peter Mook, reprints and manuscripts, 1974-1978 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Jerry Olson, Chicago Teachers' Center manuscript and brochure, 1990 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Josef Orczyk, manuscripts, 1971, undated (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Michel Petty, reprints, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Dudley Plunkett, manuscripts, 1965, 1967 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Suet-ling Pong and David Post, manuscripts, 1988, undated (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - David Post, reprints, manuscripts, correspondence, 1985-1988, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - George Psacharopoulos, reprints and manuscripts, 1970-1980 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - George Psacharopoulos, reprints and manuscripts, 1981-1984 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - George Psacharopoulos, reprints and manuscripts, 1985-1992 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - George Psacharopoulos, reprints and manuscripts, undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Jeffrey Puryear, reprints and manuscripts, 1979-1996 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Sherwin Rosen, vitae, reprints, 1972-1988 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Edward Rannells, manuscripts, 1958-1962, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Jorge Sanguinetty, manuscript, 1980 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - T. Paul Schultz, reprints and manuscripts, 1980, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - John Smyth, reprints and manuscripts, 1969-1984 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Daniel Socolow, manuscript, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - George Stigler, reprint and manuscripts, undated (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Vincent Tinto, reprints, 1973, 1981 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Jan Tinbergen, manuscripts and reprints, 1972-1973, undated (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Finis Welch, reprints and manuscripts, 1972-1989 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Robert Willis, reprints, 1979, 1986 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Douglas Windham, reprints and manuscripts, 1976, 1980 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Adrian Ziderman, manuscripts, 1989-1990 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous reprints by students, 1961-1987 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous articles by Univeristy of Chicago faculty, 1978-1991 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Ashenfalter - Burt (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Cameron - Choi (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Epstein - Jensen (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Jin Lian - King (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Knight - Mingat (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Mingat - Peterson (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Ram - Zimmerman (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Abel - Bowles (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Buchanan - Davidson (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Davies - Foster (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Foster - Johnson (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Karen - Lundberg (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Machan - Michael (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Mishkin - Owen (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Peshkin - Sen (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Shea - Woodhall, unidentified (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - World Bank staff, "International Technology Transfer" (Box 42, Folder 3)
- Series V: Restricted
  - Financial papers, 1996-1997 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1984 (Box 44, Folder 1)